-鲁道夫·斯曼兹
“没有绳子的世界是混乱的”
你那边抬高点儿 你根本没有用劲儿
Hold your end up higher. You're not holding it.
我用劲儿了
I am too.
- 你才没呢  - 我这边儿你放心
- You are not.   - Don't worry about me.
- 嘿 你的西装是炭灰色？  - 不是
- Hey, isn't that suit charcoal?   - No.
我觉得是炭灰色 炭灰色化纤的
Looks charcoal gray to me. Some gray polyester blend.
参加亲爹的葬礼 应该穿黑色的
You'd think you could find a black suit for your own father's funeral.
- 这是黑的  - 不 我确定是灰的
- It's black.   - No. I'm sure it's gray.
- 黑的  - 灰的  - 黑的！  - 灰的！
- It's black. Black!   - Gray. Gray!
- 黑的！  - 好吧 黑的
- Black!   - Fine, it's black.
这是最发灰的黑色
It's the grayest black I've ever seen.
- 是什么颜色不重要！啊！  - 啊！
- It doesn't matter what color it is! Ah!   - Oww!
对不起 爸爸 对不起！
I'm sorry, Pop. I'm sorry!
- 快！把他弄出来！  - 他现在都快到港口了
- Quick! Get him out of there!   - He's halfway to the harbor by now, bub.
不妙啊
Ah, well.
饰演：
厄尼
内森·连恩
饰演：
拉尔斯
李·伊万斯
鼠
记
捕
斯曼兹制绳厂
艾伦·西尔维斯特里
音乐：
菲登·帕帕迈克尔
摄影：
亚当·莱福金
编剧：
“我留给你们的不单是一家模范工厂…”
"I leave you not just a model factory..."
“而是更有价值的东西”
"but something infinitely more valuable."
“绳子本身… 的未来”
"The future of string... itself."
戈尔·维宾斯基
导演：
“因此 我的遗愿是…”
"And thus it is my dying wish..."
“将制绳厂 交由我的两个儿子共同经营”
"that my two sons run Smuntz String together."
太好了 竖块“出售”的牌子 看能卖多少钱
Great. Let's stick a "For Sale" sign on the lawn and see what we can get.
厄尼 爸爸没有让我们卖 他让咱们俩共同经营
Ernie, we're not supposed to sell it. We're supposed to run it together.
怎么着都行
Either way,
反正这个博物馆似的老厂子也值不了
this godforsaken museum piece is not worth a dime,
两个钱 拉尔斯
now is it, Lars?
有些事比钱要重要 厄尼
Some things are more important than money, Ernie.
我发现兜里没钱的人都爱这么说？
Notice it's always the financially challenged who say that?
哎 还没完呢
Uh, please, please.
“我的儿子们 将得到我的个人财产”
"I also bequeath to you my personal effects,"
“包括一个陶瓷蛋”
"including my ceramic egg,"
“半盒古巴雪茄”
"half box of Cuban cigars,"
噢！还有 还有…
Oh! Yes, yes, yes, yes.
“勺子 收藏品”
my-my collection of spoons."
上帝啊 大宝藏 大遗产啊
My goodness, what a treasure. What a legacy.
勺子！勺子！这么多
Spoons! Spoons! So many spoons,
一辈子都用不完
so little time.
噢！还有每个家庭都不能缺少的
Oh! And, of course, something no household should be without.
陶瓷蛋！呵呵呵
The ceramic egg! Ooh-hoo-hoo.
肯给我吧？行吗？嗯？嗯？不
Can I have the egg? Can l? Huh? Huh? No.
- 我希望你能收下  - 好 我要了！
- I want you to have it.   - Fine, I'll take it!
要是有地契之类的 记得告诉我
If you find any real estate on that desk, let me know.
没错 遗产还包括一栋房子
Well, It seems there is also a house.
- 房子？  - “诺顿街5120号”
- A house?   - Yes, "5120 Nortondale."
是多年前抵给你父亲的欠债抵押品
Your father acquired it many years ago as payment of a debt.
他一直没去住 有意思的是
He-He never lived there, but i-i-it's interesting.
以前的房主被人发现锁在阁楼上的箱子里
It seems the previous owner was found locked in a trunk in the attic.
等等 值钱吗？
Wait a minute. Is it worth anything?
当年房主用它抵押借了五万美元给工人发工资
Well, he was able to borrow $50,000 against it to pay his workers.
真的？那现在能值多少？
Really? So, what is its value today?
呃 五万美元
$50,000.
太好了 一栋破房子和一家破制绳工厂
Great. A worthless house and a broken-down string factory.
噢 好吧 今天也算没白跑一趟
Oh, well. At least the day wasn't a total loss.
谢谢 你的便宜烟
Thanks for the stogies, Pop.
哎 你不能走 厄尼 我们得看完所有的文件
Wait. You can't go. Ernie, we-we have to go through all these papers.
恕我失陪了
You'll have to excuse me.
我要接待市长
I've got a date with the mayor.
市长先生！市长先生 这边！市长先生！
Mr. Mayor! Mr. Mayor, over here! Mr. Mayor!
市长先生
Mr. Mayor,
您最近刚做了心脏分流术 是否会影响你的竞选连任？
do you think your recent triple heart bypass will affect your campaign strategy?
莱斯莉 我是来吃饭的
Now, Leslie, I'm just here to eat.
噢 市长大人 市长夫人 欢迎光临厄尼餐厅
Ah, monsieur le maire, Madame maire, welcome to Chez Ernie.
啊 您二位的大驾光临 令小店蓬荜生辉
Ah, what an honor it is to have you in my humble bistro.
请跟我来 噢 您把二位美丽的千金也带来了
Suivez-moi. Oh, you brought the little ones. The little bicycle thieves.
请坐！这是最好的位子 请
Bonjour! Our very best table.
- 您是不是瘦了？  - 呃 我…
- Have you lost a little weight?   - Oh, I...
不 不 一定是苗条并且强壮！
I think so! I think you may be buff!
噢嚯 您的美貌 令我目羡神迷
Je suisse enchante pour votre beaute.
- 您知道吧？  - 噢 厄尼先生…
- You know what I mean?   - Oh, monsieur Ernie...
恕我失陪 再见 孩子们！
Excusez-moi. Au revoir, les enfants!
唉… 往高处走不算难
Alas... The air's not so thin at the top.
故意早死 不看我成就大业
Just like the old man to die before I hit it big.
大家记住 细节是最重要的！
Remember, everyone. Attention to detail is vital!
卖相就是一切
Presentation is everything.
噢 不 不 不 不 不！必须由我亲自上菜
No, no, no, no, no! These I must deliver myself.
香橙鸭肉 配法国酱汁…(法语)
Duck a l'Orange avec du quack sauce...
噢 太棒了！(法语)
Oh, Super!
为市长先生准备的佳肴是(法语)
And for ze Mayor, la specialite de la maison,
本店的特色菜 厄尼秘制焗龙虾(法语)
Lobster Loaf a la Ernst ou la bibliotheque.
- 噢…  - 请慢用(法语)
- Oh...   - Bon appetit.
噢 你好！(法语)
Ah, bonjour!
厄尼大厨 在竞选连任前夕接待市长 你作何感想？
Chef Ernie, how does it feel to be serving the mayor on the eve of his campaign reelection?
- 呃 莱斯莉… 能叫你莱斯莉吧？  - 当然
- Well, Leslie... May I call you Leslie?   - Of course.
哦 是这样的…
Oh, this is how it...
嗯 很脆！我喜欢杏仁儿
Crunchy! Hmm. I love the almonds.
烹饪 就像喜怒无常的情妇…
Leslie, cuisine, she is a fickle mistress...
啊！看呐！
Ee-yew! Look!
一只蟑螂！
A cockroach!
这是半只蟑螂
That's only half a cockroach.
爸爸 吃了它的脑袋！
Daddy! You ate the head!
亲爱的 你还好吗？
Honey, are you okay?
又发作了！
Not again!
厄尼先生
Mr. Ernie,
请问这是意外 还是蓄意谋杀…
Was this an accident, or did you murder...
电击！
Clear!
我跳得比你好！
I can do that better!
不可能！
Impossible!
斯曼兹制绳厂
斯曼兹线绳法已经成为历史
Smuntz String is a relic of history.
现在没有人用两股麻绳来绑东西
You don't make string by twining two strands together anymore.
不 大家选用简单的 结实的单根尼龙绳
No. You make it simple, singular, strong, with nylon.
那 那不是绳子 而是尼龙线
Bu-But that's not string. Tha-That's cord.
- 完全正确  - 麻绳过时了
- Exactly.   - Twine is yesterday.
- 这是尼龙线的时代  - 泽普科财团…
- Single-strand cord is today.   - Zeppco International...
一直对你的工厂很感兴趣 但你父亲拒绝出售
has been interested in your factory for years, but your father refused to sell.
我们希望你会更聪明
We are hopin' you would be a little smarter.
我们愿意收购工厂…
Zeppco is willin' to buy you out...
并将这老古董带到21世纪
and bring this museum into the 21st century.
当然 你可以留下来担任绳子顾问
'Course, we would keep you on as a string consultant,
享受高额薪水和退休金
with a huge salary and a hefty pension.
那么…
So...
你意下如何？
what do you say?
- 儿子们…  - 厄尼
- My sons...   - Ernie.
厄尼！
Ernie!
好 稍等
Yeah. Just a sec.
我希望 你们… 收下
I want you...to have...omething.
我最宝贵的财产
My most prized possession.
呃 这是一段绳子
Oh, it's a piece of st-string.
不是普通的绳子 这是我
Not just any string. The string.
来美国第一天时 发现的
I found it my first day in America.
- 它特别在哪儿？  - 我把它装在兜里
- What's with the string?   - It's been in my pocket
六十年了 给！我要你们分享
for 60 years. Here! I want you two to share it.
也许它能将你们绑在一起
Maybe it'll bring you closer together.
- 你们最近很少交谈  - 对
- You haven't talked much lately.   - Yeah.
- 啊！你要干什么？  - 分成两半
- Ah! What are you doing?   - I'm breaking it in half.
- 不！  - 不吗？
- No!   - No?
你们要共同拥有
I want you to share it.
- 直到永远  - 行 老爸 放心
- Forever.   - Sure, Pop, sure.
呃 头50年你装着 之后 再给我
Here, uh, you carry it the first 50 years, I'll take it the next.
- 好的  - 让吗啡快点儿滴
- Sure.   - And, uh, turn up the morphine drip a little.
- 好  - 我听见了
- Sure.   - I heard that.
答应我…
Promise me...
你们永远不把…
that you will never sell...
斯曼兹制绳厂… 卖给那些大财团
Smuntz String... to one of those big conglomerates.
你们来经营
Keep it between you.
兄弟俩 一家人
Brothers. Family.
- 答应我  - 我答应你 爸爸
- Promise.   - I promise, Pop.
- 我答应你  - 意下如何？
- I promise.   - So, you were sayin'?
我只能拒绝
I'll have to pass.
什么？
What?
“没有绳子 世界就乱套了”
"A world without string is chaos."
好不容易 斯曼兹这个姓能值点儿钱！
For once the Smuntz name was worth something!
你 你… 你以前喜欢绳子啊！
You...You used to love string!
那是以前 在我和制绳大王的儿子约会的时候！
That was before, when I was dating the son of a wealthy string magnate!
现在不了
Not now,
因为我的丈夫只是个拥有半栋危楼的穷光蛋！
when I am married to the half-owner of a worthless deathtrap!
我以为我立场坚定 你会很高兴的！
I thought you'd be happy! I stood up for myself today!
艾普尔 我对工厂有新想法
April, I've got new ideas for the factory.
我有一个大计划！
You know, I've got big plans!
你还不懂吗？一直以来你有的只是计划
Don't you see, Lars? That's all you've ever had are plans.
我的美好年华就这样没了
But my life is passing me by,
我要的不只是这些！
and I...I need more!
中产阶级是死路一条 我不想死
There's no air in the middle class, Lars. I can't breathe here.
求你 艾普尔 你不要走
Please, April, don't go.
要走的不是我
I'm not going anywhere.
转眼之间 愉快的假期被打乱了…
In a few brief moments, the joy of the holidays was shattered...
很多人的世界从此改变
and the world changed for many people.
本市市长 今天下午四点三十分
Mayor McKrinkle died this afternoon at 4:30 p.m.,
在圣母慈善医院
at Our Lady of
不治身亡 医生说 正式的死因…
Sorrows Hospital. Doctors here say the official cause of death is...
是用餐时受到惊吓所引起的心力衰竭
heart failure due to the mayor's recent culinary disaster.
码头上往日风光无限的厄尼大厨餐厅…
And once the hottest restaurant on the wharf, Chez Ernie...
倍受指责 将于今日强行拆除
has been condemned and scheduled for demolition.
呃 对不起！
Excuse me!
我没说要给干酪三明治加酸豆 很抱歉
I-I don't think I ordered my cheese sandwich with capers. I'm sorry.
真对不起
I'm sorry.
悲剧的罪魁祸首是厄尼·斯曼兹…
If there is a villain in this tragedy, it is Ernie Smuntz.
本地餐饮业的神话人物…
Mythological figures in the local restaurant industry...
- 嗨 厄尼  - 什么？
- Hi, Ernie,   - What?
- 你又上电视了！  - 噢
- you're on TV again!   - Oh.
这叫什么？我告诉你
You know what this is? I'll tell ya.
- 欲加之罪 何患无辞  - 不要酸豆
- Guilt by accusation.   - No capers.
不要酸豆？就剩烤干酪怎么吃？
No capers? But that's just grilled cheese. What's the point?
这种客人应该去猪圈！
Why don't they eat out of a trough?
听着
All right.
是哪个笨蛋把三明治给退回来的？
Which one of you palateless sheep sent my sandwich back?
嗨 厄尼！
Hi, Ernie!
拉尔斯？
Lars?
嗨
Hey.
我在厨房做饭
When I'm in the kitchen, I cook.
不可能管着整个餐厅的所有事
I can't control every single thing that goes on in there.
大家都指责你 真的很不公平
You know, it really isn't fair for everybody to blame you.
你没有做错什么
You didn't do anything wrong.
对呀 可社会需要找个替罪羊
Yes, but society always needs someone to persecute.
需要把好人丑化成魔鬼 伽利略当年也是这样
A scapegoat, someone to demonize. The same thing happened to Galileo.
是吗？难以置信
Really? That's unbelievable.
他的蟑螂也吃死人了？
With a cockroach and everything?
不 重要的是 我把一切都投入到餐馆
No. The point is, I put everything I had into that restaurant.
这是我的工作 我的家
It was my livelihood and my home.
客人一口咬错地方 一切就没了
In one fatal bite, it was all taken away from me.
我们只能卖掉工厂
If only we could sell the factory.
我很想请你住到我的家 可是艾普尔把我赶出来了
Uh...I'd let you stay with me, you know, but, uh, April threw me out.
- 噢 那太糟了  - 是啊 不过不要担心我 厄尼
- Oh, that's too bad.   - Yeah, well, don't worry about me, though, Ernie.
这是暂时的 艾普尔从高中起就是这样
Th-This is temporary. April's been like this since high school.
- 她会想通的 呃…  - 你来看看
- She'll be back. I...   - Would you look at them?
睡在大街上 太惨了
Sleeping in the street. Pitiful.
我也想睡在房子里！
If I had a house, I'd sleep in it!
- 厄尼 你还记得小时候我们有多亲吗？  - 不记得
- Ernie, do you remember how close we were as kids?   - No.
嘿！圣诞快乐！
Hey! Merry Christmas!
对 以前我也风光过
Yeah, I was on top once too.
但顶峰只有一条路 那就是下坡路 下坡路！
But there's only one way to go from there, and that's down, baby, down!
厄尼
Ernie.
厄尼！厄尼 那是两毛五的硬币呀
Ernie! Ernie, there was a quarter in there.
两毛五？你真是目光短浅 拉尔斯
A quarter? You think so small, Lars.
♪ 我将迎来那平安夜 ♪
# Christmas Eve will find me #
看看你现在 你没有家 没有老婆 没有钱…
Look at the bigger picture. You have no home, you have no wife, you have no money.
♪ 爱的光芒闪烁不断 ♪
# Where the love light gleams, #
没有可谋生的才能 你却视而不见？
You have no discernible talents. How can you ignore that?
厄尼 这是圣诞节
Ernie, it's Christmas.
♪ 圣诞节我会回到家中 ♪
# I'll be home for Christmas #
与其抱怨没有什么 不如对已经拥有的东西感恩
Instead of dwelling on what we don't have, we should be thankful for what we do have.
♪ 即使只在我的梦里… ♪
# If I'm only in my dreams... #
爱泼斯坦面包店
■
欢迎回家
像垃圾场
What a dump.
噢！爸爸居然没有跟我们提过这个房子
Wow! I can't believe Pops never told us about this house.
真大呀
It's huge.
这正像老爸喜欢的房子
This is just the kind of house I'd expect him to have.
跟他一样 又冷又吓人
It's just like him. Cold and spooky.
- 噢！你也打了吗？  - 什么？
- Wow! Did you feel that?   - What?
打冷颤 你不该那样说我们的爸爸
I got a chill. You shouldn't talk about Pop like that.
是吗？那你看这样呢？
Really? What's this do for you?
你真是小气 喜欢绳子的老笨蛋！
Thanks for nothing, you string-sucking old loon!
他 他不是那意思
He didn't mean it, Pop.
厄尼！厄尼！
Ernie! Ernie!
就一张床 扔硬币吧
Only one bed. I'll flip you for it.
人头
Heads.
厄尼
E-Ernie?
厄尼 厄尼
Ernie. Ernie.
- 睡着了吗？  - 是的
- You asleep?   - I was.
这么吵你都能睡得着？
How can you sleep through that?
- 怎么了？我什么都没听见  - 嘘 嘘 这个
- What? I don't hear anything.   - Shh-shh-shh-shh. That.
你听 听到了吗？是楼上传来的声音
Listen. Hear it? It's coming from upstairs.
樟脑球
Mothballs.
嗷 快住手！嘿！噢！
He-Hey, stop it! Hey! Ow!
厄尼！厄尼！
Ernie! Ernie!
等等 等等 别叫了！
Wait. Wait a minute. Stop. Stop!
你看 别叫了 只是一个玩具而已
Look. Look, look, look. It's only a toy.
啊 闭嘴！
Ah, shut up!
声音是从那儿来的！
It's coming from up there!
一 二 三！
One, two, three!
- 是一只老鼠  - 什么？
- It's just a mouse.   - What?
一只小老鼠 不用理它
It's just a mouse. Never mind.
哎 这儿有几张海报
Hey, there are some posters up here.
噢！别乱动！
Oh! Stand still!
啊！
Ah!
- 是设计图  - 哇噢！
- They're blueprints.   - Wow!
等等 你看这日期 1876年
Wait a minute. Look at this date. 1876.
有一百年历史的房子应该能值点儿钱
A centennial house could actually be worth something.
瞧 这一定是建筑师的名字 瞧这儿
Look, this must be the architect. Here, look.
“查尔斯·莱尔·拉鲁”
"Charles Lyle LaRue."
查尔斯·莱尔·拉鲁
Charles Lyle Larue.
查尔斯·莱尔·拉鲁？
Charles Lyle LaRue?
历史协会
查尔斯·莱尔·拉鲁
Charles Lyle LaRue.
查尔斯·莱尔·拉鲁！
Charles Lyle LaRue!
我站在拉鲁不为人知的杰作当中！
I'm actually standing in the missing LaRue!
- 粗犷 不失细腻  - 古典而又反传统
- It's bold yet subtle.   - Classical yet nontraditional.
传说中的遗作
The missing LaRue.
据说是拉鲁被关进精神病院之前 最后的作品
The rumored design completed shortly before his committal is a rumor no more.
精神病院？
Before his committal?
噢 很真高兴他在去精神病院之前盖好了这房子
Well, I'm just glad he finished the place before they carted him off to the laughing academy.
那么 像这样华丽的建筑值多少钱？
So, what do you think a magnificent edifice like this is worth?
当然 是在翻修之后
Properly restored, of course.
这个嘛 他设计的“灵堂”买到了六…
Well, his Parma Charnel House went for six...
而且是十年前 造型也不如这精美
But that was ten years ago, and it didn't have this exquisite molding.
懂了 造型精美最重要
I see. I can't get enough of good molding.
- 听见了吗？他说能卖到六十万  - 厄尼
- Did you hear that? $600,000.   - Ernie.
亚历山大·法尔科！
Alexander Falko!
让开！
Back!
二位 祝贺你们
Gentlemen, congratulations.
- 你们发现了宝藏  - 谢谢
- Congratulations on your find.   - Thank you.
我非常崇拜拉鲁
I'm a great admirer of LaRue.
给我一杯雨水
Glass of rainwater, please.
法尔科先生是世上头号拉鲁收藏家
Yes, Mr. Falko is the world's leading collector of LaRues.
- 哦  - 哦 就像是收集邮票 只不过更大？
- Ah.   - Ah, sort of like collecting stamps, but they're bigger, right?
我直说了吧 拉鲁 我有他的书 我有他的信
I'll get to the point. LaRue. I have his books. I have his letters.
你们看这双鞋
You see these shoes?
- 拉鲁的？  - 不 但拉鲁一定喜欢
- LaRues?   - No, but I'm sure he would have loved them.
蔬菜 小吃… 我拥有…
Vegetarian snack. I own...
四十二幢拉鲁的建筑
Forty-two LaRue houses.
四十二 我希望能变成四十三
Forty-two. I want to make it 43.
我怎样才能如愿以偿？
You tell me how I'm going to do this.
告诉我我要怎么做 你们帮个忙 说 我该怎么做？
Tell me how I will do this. You help me. How will I do this?
很高兴你有这想法
Well, I'm, uh, glad you asked.
他设计的“灵堂”能卖六…
His, uh, Parma Charnel House went for six,
而且是十年前 造型也差一些
but that was ten years ago, and it didn't have this molding.
这种精美的大宅子 以现在的行情起码得翻倍
I see, a find like this in today's market is worth twice as much.
- 他对拉鲁很懂行  - 我愿意认罪
- He's a LaRue connoisseur.   - Guilty as charged.
先生们 我来给你们开个价
Gentlemen, I'm going to make you an offer.
不… 我不可能那么傻 任凭你的摆布
No, no, no, no, no, I couldn't possibly be so crass as to allow you to do that.
欢迎参加拍卖会
But you are welcome to come to the auction.
- 拍卖？  - 拍卖？  - 拍卖 没错
- Auction?   - Auction?   - Auction, yes.
剥夺他人购买拉鲁遗作的机会 非常不公平
It would be grossly unfair of us to deprive others of the chance to bid on the missing LaRue.
我要跟我哥哥单独说句话 行吗？
May I have just one moment with my brother, please?
- 哦 当然可以  - 谢谢 失陪一下  - 没问题
- Sure. Of course.   - Thank you Excuse me.
这算什么？
What is this?
- 这算什么？不 不  - 我也是第一次听说…
- What is this? No. No.   - It's the first I've heard of...
- 你到底想干什么？  - 我干什么？让你的祈祷灵验
- What are you doing?   - What am I doing? I'm answering your prayers.
把买家聚在一起
These pigeons are ripe for the plucking.
让他们自相残杀 比着出高价
Put them in a room together. Try and outbid each other?
- 很容易就能卖到七八十万  - 噢 老哥 真聪明！
- We can make $700,000, $800,000 easy.   - Oh, man, smart!
噢！
Ooh!
- 接受现实吧 你…  - 不！不！你闭嘴！  - 那么
- You're going to get this one. You...   - Don't talk to me! Shh!   - So,
拍卖会最早可以安排在哪天呢？
when is the, uh, earliest we can set the auction?
我想 筹备工作一周之内就能做好
Well, I suppose all arrangements could be completed within the week.
- 那就一周  - 很好！
- A week it is.   - Great!
- 你们比看着聪明  - 谢谢
- You're smarter than you look.   - Thank you.
但要知道…
But know this.
我这辈子从没花过一千万以上买房子！
I have never paid more than $10 million for a house in my life!
好的 改天见
Okay, see you then.
对 谢谢你的到访
Yeah. Thanks for stopping by.
一千万包亚麻餐巾
Ten million linen napkins.
五百万包顶级纯棉细纱
Five million bales of top-grade cotton fiber.
四万个带旋转托盘的加热灯
Forty thousand hot lamps complete with rotating plate-warming trays.
两千台麻绳纺车 在灯光下闪闪发光
Two thousand twine threaders, gleaming under real lights.
属于我的五星级连锁餐厅
My own chain of five-star gourmet restaurants.
艾普尔想什么都行！车 大衣 瓷器
April can have anything she's ever wanted! Cars, coats, china.
她喜欢瓷器
She loves china.
我要建一个奥林匹克规格的游泳池…
I'm gonna build an Olympic-sized swimming pool...
装满朗姆鸡尾酒 请一大堆姑娘
and fill it with pina coladas and a college sorority.
可惜老爸没有看过这个！
If only Pop were here to see this house!
他看过 只是太傻不知道卖
He did. He just wasn't smart enough to sell it.
拉尔斯 我们转运了 美好的未来就在眼前
Lars, we've turned a corner. Our future is staring us in the face.
我们只需要抓住它 刷上酱汁 咽下去！
All we have to do is grab it, baste it, and scarf it down!
呵呵！找到小朋友的窝了！
Aha! We've finally found our friend's home!
我要送你个小礼物
Well, I bought a little present for ya, buddy.
厄尼 那只是个小老鼠 有必要弄死它吗？
Ernie, i-it's just a little mouse. Do we really have to kill it?
当然 听我说 一个小祸害能毁了一切
Yes. Listen to me. A single vermin can bring you down.
我有经验
Believe me, I know.
- 睡得不错吧  - 嗯！像婴儿一样
- I trust you slept well.   - Oh! Like a baby.
昨晚你有没有听见 呃…
Hey, last night, did you happen to hear the, uh...
- 哦 是啊 去看看  - 好
- Oh, yeah. Let's see.   - Yeah.
- 跑到哪儿去了？  - 不知道 也许夹子自己合上了
- Well, where'd he go?   - I don't know. Maybe it snapped by itself.
难以置信
I don't believe it.
它合上了老鼠夹 吃掉橄榄 留下橄榄核来嘲笑我们
He snapped the trap, ate the olive, and left the pit just to mock us.
我看你把它想得太高明了
I think you're giving him a little too much credit.
老鼠不嘲笑人 它们不懂幽默或讽刺
Mice don't mock. They don't have a sense of humor or irony.
它不会穿着便服 坐在洞里 品着白兰地
He's not sitting in his hole in a smoking jacket sipping cognac,
咯咯地笑着说“我留下了核”
and giggling to himself, "I left the pit."
夹子是自己合上的 橄榄弹出来被老鼠吃了
The trap snapped itself, the olive flew off, and he ate it.
就这么简单 如果它知道我们来了
It's that simple. But now that he knows we're here,
肯定躲到一英里以外去了
he won't come within a mile of us.
我们以后不会再看到那…
I don't think we'll be seeing any more of that...
老鼠！
Mouse!
- 啊哈！噢！  - 哎哟！
- Aha! Ow!   - Ah!
你要干嘛？你个白痴
What are you doing, ya stupid nitwit?
快给我！别让它跑了！
Don't! Give me that! Don't let him get away!
吔！
Yeah!
白痴！
Idiot!
你想要我的命吗？
Are you trying to kill me?
啊
Ah,
啊 那只老鼠！
the mouse!
你起来 让我看看！
Let me see. Let me see!
看着它了吗？
Can you see him?
把干酪拿过来
Get me my Gouda.
- 小心 小心！  - 别 别碰我 小心夹子
- Careful, careful!   - Don't. Don't touch me. You'll snap it.
- 你这么放不对  - 别动 我要集中精神 行吗？
- You're not doin' it right.   - Please, let me concentrate, will you?
- 小心点儿放 别触动机关  - 我已经非常小心了
- Put it on carefully.   - I'm putting it on carefully.
我没有… 噢 冷静 这是干酪
I'm not... Oh, relax. It's cheese.
祝你胃口好
Bon appetit.
这就行了 嗯？
That takes care of that. Huh?
嘿！
Hey!
嘿！是你扔的吗？
Hey! What are you doin'?
拉尔斯！过来帮个忙
Lars! Gimme a hand with this.
这浴缸和房子的风格般配吗？
Are you sure this tub fits in with the rest of the house?
这是“按摩浴缸” 拉尔斯 “按摩”浴缸啊
Jacuzzi tub, Lars. It's a Jacuzzi tub.
而这不是一般的房子 这是拉鲁
And this isn't just a house. It's a LaRue.
二者当然很般配
Of course it fits in with the decor.
- 奢华是永恒的  - 浴缸多少钱啊？厄尼
- Luxury is timeless.   - How much, Ernie?
打完折 一千两百块
It was a steal at $1,200.
一千两百块？
Twelve hundred dollars?
你把所有的钱都拿去买浴缸了！
You spent our last money on a tub!
是“按摩”浴缸！
A Jacuzzi tub!
想挣钱就得先投入
You have to spend money to make money.
他们送了一个纸板美人儿 作为赠品
And they threw in the cardboard lady just to sweeten the deal.
啊
Oh,
还好…
Well...
你不觉得有点儿太多了吗？
Don't you think this is a little much?
永远不要低估对手
Never underestimate your opponent.
你看 这家伙有办法 合上老鼠夹偷东西吃
Let's say he has mastered a way to empty a mousetrap without getting caught.
现在只要它触发这个
If he snaps one of these babies,
就会引起连锁反应 它会乱窜
a chain reaction will start snapping them all. He'll panic,
从概率上说 至少有一个夹子能夹住它
and the law of averages says one of them has to nab him.
不赖啊
Not bad.
是的 你看 我喜欢多动动脑子
Yes. Well, I like to use both sides of my brain.
来吧 去睡觉
Come on. Let's hit the sack.
噢 好
All right.
- 想出办法没有？  - 闭嘴
- Have you figured it out yet?   - Shut up.
我正在想 正在想！
I'm thinking. I'm thinking!
厄尼 看！
Ernie. Ernie!
千万不要动 它死定了
Keep perfectly still. This is it.
- 它要干什么？  - 不知道
- What's he doing?   - I dunno.
挺厉害
That was good.
嘘！它要去吃樱桃！
Shh! He's goin' for the cherries!
你不是说它爱吃干酪吗？
I thought you said mice like Gouda.
这是早上！干酪太腻 它需要水果来提神
Not in the morning! Cheese tires them out. They need fruit for energy.
- 啊！  - 噢 不！
- Ah!   - Oh, no!
往那儿跑了！
There he goes!
- 通电！  - 好了！
- Juice!   - Got it!
游戏结束了！
This game is over!
- 该管用了！  - 是啊
- I think it's working!   - Yeah.
哇啊！嗯！吸到东西了
Whoa! Uh! I felt something.
继续吸！
Keep sucking!
见鬼 老鼠可真臭！
Goddamn, that mouse stinks!
对 死耗子就是这个味儿
Yeah. Dead animals always do.
继续吸！厄尼
Keep sucking, Ernie!
噢 是的 这下它完蛋了！
Oh, yeah, this'll get him!
终止抵押房产赎回权的通知
你这是什么东西？
What's this?
你没有按期还款
We're foreclosing on your house.
所以银行要没收房产
You've quit paying your mortgage.
噢 等等 这一定是个误会 房款早就付清了
Oh, wait a minute. I think there's been some mistake. This house is paid for.
付清了 但你又抵押借款了
No, it was paid for, but you borrowed against it.
不偿还一千二百美元借款 房子就没收
If you don't pay the $1,200 overdue, we repossess it.
- 一千二百美元？  - 呃 哪天还钱？
- Twelve hundred dollars?   - Well, how long do we have?
一周之内
One week from, uh,
- 从五天前算起  - 那… 呃 那 那就剩两天了！
- five days ago.   - But, uh, that's two days!
我们现在没有时间和精力应付这些小事儿
We don't have the time or energy to deal with these petty problems now.
我们正在给房子改头换面
We're in the midst of an extensive renovation.
看来你们干得不错
Looks like you're off to a great start.
你去向老板预支一点儿工资吧
You could ask your boss at Rimpy's for an advance.
等拍卖之后就还给他
You can pay him back after the auction.
你不能过几个星期再给工人发薪水吗？
Couldn't you ask your workers to forfeit their salaries for a few weeks?
你是老板嘛
You are the boss.
要不是你把钱都拿去买按摩浴缸
If you hadn't spent all our money on that tub,
我们能够还清贷款的
we might be able to pay the mortgage.
现在抱怨也于事无补
It doesn't help to start crying now.
不  不！
No, no!
猫猫！我的猫猫！
No, Fluffy! No!
不！不！
No! I want my kitty!
不 不！
No, no, no!
啊 这只真可爱
That one's cute.
不行 它没有杀手的本能
No. He doesn't have that killer instinct.
早上好 先生们 我叫莫里 需要我帮忙吗？
Morning, gentlemen. I'm Maury. Anything I can help you with?
呃 嗨 莫里 我们想养一只猫
Uh, hi, Maury. W-We need a cat.
找好想要的
Find the one you want,
我亲自给它做绝育手术
and I'll spay or neuter it myself.
这些都是小猫
Well, these are all kittens.
我们想要只大的 经验丰富的
We were hoping for an older cat. One with experience.
你们想要的真不多见 一般人都喜欢小猫
That's a switch. Most people like the cute little ones.
- 要什么经验？  - 抓老鼠
- Experience with what?   - Mouse hunting.
所有的猫都会抓老鼠
Oh, all cats are good mousers.
呃 对 但问题是
Yes, but you see,
我家有好多好多相扑选手级别的特大号老鼠
we have huge rats the size of sumo wrestlers, and lots of them.
所以我们需要一只凶猛的猫 有精神病史的最好
So, we really need a ferocious feline, preferably with a history of mental illness.
我们要… 最凶残的
I'm talkin'...one mean pussy.
对！恶毒的猫 不招人痛的
Yeah! A vicious cat, difficult to love.
你的笼子里面有这种猫吗？
Do you have any of those knocking around your cages?
真是太巧了 有一只送不出去的猫
Funny you should ask. I had all but given up on anyone wanting him.
我们正要第二次给它下毒
We were about to gas him again.
- 第二次？  - 第二次？
- Again?   - Again?
它大半辈子都被关在这箱子里
He's spent most of his whole life in that box, I expect.
哥斯拉
“哥斯拉”？
"Catzilla"?
这是清洁工给它取的名字
The guys who clean up call him that.
当然 你们可以随便改
But, uh, you can call him anything you want.
我觉得 它长得像“毛球”
I'd say he looks like a "Fluffy."
哦 可怜的哥斯拉
Ah, poor little Catzilla.
你想要个家对吗？你想要离开这里
You want a home, don't you? You wanna get out of here.
那你就得好好地杀 杀 杀老鼠
Well, you're gonna have to kill, kill, kill for it.
你是笨猫 对吗？
You're a stupid cat, aren't you?
嘿 嘿 哦 你长得很难看！
Yes, you are. And you're ugly. Extremely ugly!
- 噢！你这个小混蛋  - 我们要了
- Oh! Oh, you little bastard.   - We'll take him.
来 啊
Here, boy.
噢 肯定是闻到气味儿了
Ooh...He's got the scent now.
对 抓老鼠
Yeah, uh, go get'im, boy.
慢点儿 慢点儿 别冲动！
Oh, easy, easy, easy, easy!
噢 我几乎要为老鼠难过了
Wow. I almost feel sorry for the little fella.
- 几乎！  - 几乎！
- Almost!   - Almost!
现在不用担心老鼠的问题了…
It's time to stop worrying about that mouse...
想想去哪儿找一千两百块钱吧
and start thinking about how we're going to locate $1,200.
别担心 厄尼
Don't worry, Ernie.
工人们会帮我们的
The workers will help us out.
事实上 我们连一毛钱都没有
You see, the truth is, we don't actually have any money.
所以 我们不得不
We may have to
晚一两个月再给大家发工资
defer your next paycheck or-or two.
我和我的哥哥要偿还房子的抵押款
So my brother and I can pay the mortgage on the house.
那是拉鲁的作品！
It's the missing LaRue!
不 请大家不要这样
I mean, there's no need for violence, you know.
把东西放下 哇噢！
Put that thing down. Whoa!
泽普克财团 业务代表
…一千万现金收购…
厄尼！
Ernie!
- 出什么事了？  - 那些工人…
- What's the matter?   - Well, the, uh, the workers.
他们的反应不像我预想的那么积极
They didn't react as positively as I had hoped.
是吗？呃 你要干嘛？
No? Uh, what are you doing?
你能从窗户钻出去吗？
Uh, you could fit through this window, right?
什么？
What?
哦 呃 应该可以
Wh... I guess so.
很好
Come on.
开门！
Open the door!
噢 可是 拉尔斯 这是我们最后的办法！
Oh, but, Lars, that was our last resort!
我们只能去别处弄钱了
Well, we're gonna have to find the money someplace else.
该死的！
Damn it!
收购合同
拟议收购：
布里克县 斯曼兹制绳厂
泽普科财团
你们这些吸血鬼！
You vampires!
哎呀 可惜没有人愿意买咱们的工厂
Gosh, it's a shame nobody's interested in buying the factory.
对 对 真可惜
Yeah, yeah, it's a shame.
谁会犯傻买这个玩意儿 不是吗？
But who'd be stupid enough to buy the factory, right?
哈哈哈 对
Yeah.
哦 你一定是凯撒
Ah, you must be Caesar.
凯撒先生 很高兴您这么快赶过来
Well, Mr. Caesar, uh, glad you could get here so quickly...
嘘！
Shh!
有老鼠
You have mice.
他真历害
He's good.
诺顿街5120号
5120 Nortondale.
一月四号 早晨八点整
January 4. 08:00 hours.
别忘了带牙膏和防水外套
Don't forget to get toothpaste and Saran Wrap.
我们急着出门 我只想说 这老鼠很难缠
We're in sort of a hurry. Uh, I just want to warn you about this mouse.
对 房子里有石棉
Yeah. You got asbestos, all right.
大部分都铺在天花板
I'll bet it's up in the ceiling, mostly.
拆除的话大概需要一到两天
Shouldn't take me more than a day or two to remove it.
- 他是说给老鼠听的  - 好吧
- He said it was for the mice.   - All right.
好 我懂了
Okay, then.
呃 呃 那我 那我们… 呃 上楼去吧
Um, uh, so, we're gonna go upstairs.
呃 对 我们全到楼上去
All right, well, we'll all go upstairs.
是的
Yeah.
- 非常好  - 是的
- Okay, then.   - Yeah.
你们干嘛？
What are you doing?
- 老鼠没在听  - 噢
- He's not listening anymore.   - Oh.
太好了 您真专业
Good. Well, you're the expert.
请您不惜一切代价干掉那只老鼠
I just hope you can take care of this, whatever it takes.
整个星期我们都想抓住它
We've been trying to catch this little menace all week.
这就是你们的问题
Here's your problem.
一般人不懂得除鼠的心理学常识
Normal people are not psychologically equipped to catch mice.
你们得进入老鼠的脑袋
You have to get inside their mind.
了解它的想法和需要
You have to know what they want... need.
像老鼠一样思维
You have to think like a mouse.
如果能从老鼠的视角思考…
If you can do that... if you can think like a mouse...
你们就能预测它的行动
you can anticipate their moves.
然后 砰！
Then, boom!
永别了 老鼠
Sayonara, mouse.
呃 装备不错啊…
Well, got some great stuff...
啊！
Whoa!
别碰那个！
Never touch that!
好！
All right!
那是什么？
What is it?
- 大炸弹  - 那是杀跳蚤的！
- The big one.   - It's a flea bomb!
对老鼠也管用
Works on mice too.
是吗？
Yeah?
那就好 入侵者赶紧走吧
Well, it better. Because we can't handle any more intrusions.
当然 这是你的想法
Sure. That's how you perceive it.
对于那只老鼠
But to that mouse,
你们才是入侵者
you are the intruder.
如果加班加点 应该能够生产出足够的绳子交货
I think if we work fast, we can make enough string to meet our orders.
这么想就对了 我生产几箱 就能保住拉鲁
That's the spirit. Just a few cases, so we can keep the LaRue.
- 不 等等！  - 祝你好运  - 你要去哪儿？
- Good luck.   - Wait! Where are you going?
- 我去办点事儿 待会儿见  - 你不帮忙吗？
- Aren't you gonna help?   - I have to run a little errand.
待会儿见啊 哎 生产价值一千二的绳子
All you have to do is make $1,200 worth.
要花多少时间？
How long can that take?
划根火柴 用火吓住他们
Light a match. They're frightened by fire.
不讲卫生的动物
Unsanitary creature.
竟然在饭厅大便
Defecating in the dining room.
九点十五分 发现证物
09:15. Evidence found.
老鼠排泄物 啊 雄性
Mus communis. Ugh. Male.
十 到十二厘米长
Ten to, uh, twelve centimeters long,
什么 嗯…
with a... hmm...
什么？
What's this?
轻度缺钙体质
A slight calcium deficiency.
有意思
That's interesting.
哦 嗨 我是斯曼兹制绳厂的厄尼·斯曼兹
Uh, hi. This is Ernest Smuntz of Smuntz String.
泽普克财团 业务代表
您是泽普科财团的业务代表吗？
Is this the business representative for Zeppco International?
威尼？哦 嗨 威尼 很高兴能叫你威尼
Vinny? Hi, Vinny. Oh, I'm glad I can call you Vinny.
呃 我弟弟和我打算重新考虑你们的慷慨的报价
Uh, my brother and I have decided to reconsider your generous offer.
我想和你谈谈卖厂的事
I'd love to discuss selling our factory to you.
呃 呃 呃… 不 别在办公室
Oh, no, not at the office.
我们中午在埃尔曼广场的钟楼底下见好吗？
How about Ellman Square under the big clock at noon?
呃 你一定是拉尔斯·斯曼兹的太太？
Uh, you, you must be Mrs. Lars Smuntz?
恐怕这个身份很快就要变了
I'm afraid that status is in transition.
哦 拉尔斯在吗？
Oh, well, is Lars in?
- 我想和他谈谈拍卖会筹备的事  - 拍卖会？
- I'd like to discuss preparations for the auction.   - The auction?
当心 拉尔斯 你会着凉的
Careful, Lars. You might catch a cold.
艾普尔！
April!
你似乎需要暖暖身子
You look like you could use some warming up.
十三点正 开启“抓耗子能手2000”
13:00 hours. I've activated the Squeak Seeker 2000.
猎物将无所遁形
I'm about to join with the prey.
等离子屏幕出现故障 待命
I'm experiencing malfunction with the plasma screen. Stand by.
垃圾
Junk.
报废了
Nothing works.
什么？
What?
噢 完了！
Ah, nuts!
心电图 颈椎 胸腔 盆骨 X光扫描 快 快！
EKG, a C-spine, a chest X ray and pelvis. Now move!
一千两百块呀
Twelve hundred dollars.
躺好 斯曼兹先生 你被公共汽车撞了
Lie still, Mr. Smuntz. You've just been hit by a bus.
我很好 几点了？
I feel fine. What time is it?
可能有脑震荡 我们需要拍一系列的X光片
You may have had a concussion. We're gonna do a series of X rays.
你不明白 医生 我必须离开这儿
You don't understand, Doc. I have to get out of here.
说不定还有机会
I might still have a chance.
你的帽子呢
We saved your hat.
- 对不起 是家属吗？  - 对 亲姐妹
- I'm sorry. Are you family?   - Yes, we are sisters.
太好了 请你们填几张表
Great. There's some paperwork I need for you to fill out.
他能捐赠器官吗？
Is he an organ donor?
一个字都别让她们写 我不认识她们
Don't let them fill anything out. I don't even know them.
哦 我叫希尔德 她是英格丽
Oh, I'm Hilde, and this is Ingrid.
- 从比利时来的发型模特儿  - 充满异域风情
- We are hair models from Belgium.   - Belgian hair models. How exotic.
听我说 医生 我要打电话
Listen to me, Doc. I need to find a phone
不然我就会错过人生中最重要的事
before I miss out on the deal of my life.
- 你哥哥有点儿神智不清了  - 我不是她的哥哥！
- I think your brother's a little delirious.   - I am not their brother!
我没有妹妹！
I don't have any sisters!
厄尼 你没事吧？我一听说就赶来了
Ernie, are you okay? I came as soon as I heard.
你干嘛穿粉外套？
Why are you wearing a pink overcoat?
因为艾普尔给了我一千两百美元！
Because April gave us the twelve hundred dollars!
她无缘无故给你钱？她早知道拍卖的事了？
She gave you the money? You don't think she heard about the auction?
不会 在和好之前 我一个字都没有跟她说
No. I didn't even tell her about the auction until after she took me back.
她突然来到工厂 脱掉外套 求我要她
She just showed up at the factory, took off her coat and begged me to take her.
噢 那种激情迸发的场面
Oh. We made love in a way
我只在“动物世界”里面见过
I've only ever seen in nature films.
噢 我真不敢相信
Wow. I almost can't believe it.
我能再开一家餐厅了 你和艾普尔和好了
I'll be able to open up another restaurant, you're back with April,
我们还保住了那个不值钱的工厂
and you'll even be able to keep that worthless factory.
有意思 你居然说工厂不值钱
You know it's funny that you call the factory worthless,
有一件事情 我想我应该跟你说过…
because, well, there's something l probably should have mentioned before...
是吗？呃 我也得跟你坦白一件事
Yeah? Well, I guess I have something to confess too.
那辆是凯撒的车吗？
Hey, isn't that Caesar's truck?
- 噢 我的天呐！  - 凯撒！出什么事了？
- Oh, my God!   - Caesar! What happened?
- 别这样 他受不了  - 好好想想 老鼠死了吗？
- Please, sir. He's not well.   - Try to think. Did you kill the mouse?
什么？什么？
What's that? Horse?
臭东西！我才不吃呢
Fiendish! I won't eat it.
你们是怎么找到他的？
How'd you find him? Where was he?
- 有人报警 但不说话  - 消灭他们！
- 911 call. No voice.   - Exterminate them!
我们听到尖叫声
We could hear screaming in the background.
他被锁在阁楼的箱子里
He was locked in a trunk in the attic.
有消息就会通知你们
We'll call you if we get any leads.
这是什么？
What's that?
啊 快放下 那是什么？
Ah. Put that down. What is that?
呃 有声音！
Uh, that tickles!
我们要对付的不是一只普通的老鼠
I don't think we're dealing with an ordinary mouse.
我的厨房！
My kitchen!
看起来凯撒想做个三明治
Looks like Caesar decided to make himself a sandwich.
腌菜 芝麻菜和酸豆
Pickles, arugula and capers.
涂奶酪的这一面烤过…
He toasted the side with the cheese...
但另一面没有 所以菜叶还新鲜
but not the other side, so the arugula doesn't wilt.
这窍门儿它也懂？
How did he know that?
- 你好  - 你好
- Hello.   - Hello.
- 看见它了吗？  - 对 我看见了
- Do you see him?   - Yeah, I see him.
拉尔斯 我卡住了！拉我出来！
Lars, I'm stuck! Get me out of here!
- 我去拿手电筒  - 憋死我了！
- I-I'll get a flashlight.   - I can't breathe!
快点儿！
Hurry!
- 行了 厄尼 手电筒在这儿  - 看出来了
- Here, Ernie, I got it.   - I can see that.
挺住 厄尼 手电筒不亮了
Hang on, Ernie. The flashlight's broken.
哎 厄尼 是火柴
Okay, Ernie. I got a light.
太好了
Great.
拉尔斯
Lars,
你闻到了吗？
do you smell something?
像煤气味儿
Smells like gas.
你要干什么？
What are you gonna do?
我要一劳永逸 干掉那该死的小杂种
I'm gonna kill that unspeakable thing once and for all.
- 好了 厄尼 不要…  - 别拦着我！拉尔斯
- Come on, Ernie, no, no...   - Stand back, Lars!
我要替天行道！
I'm a man on a mission!
意外就是这样发生的！好了 厄尼
Look, this is how accidents happen! Come on, Ernie.
- 行啊！  - 放下枪 冷静一点儿 厄尼
- Ok!   - Put the gun down. Calm down. Come on.
我要一枪轰掉那毛茸茸的小脑袋
I'm gonna blow his furry little head off,
我要让它冒坏水的脑浆子一路溅到天国！
and I'm gonna splatter his devious little mouse brain from here to kingdom come!
不 不 不！你会把墙打成窟窿的
No, no! You're gonna blow a hole in the wall.
- 那我也觉得值！  - 不要这样！厄尼
- It'll be worth it!   - Come onz, Ernie!
想想拍卖会！看在上帝份上！
Think of the auction! For God's sakes!
- 想想钱！厄尼  - 钱？
- Think of the money, Ernie!   - The money?
墙上有弹孔 买家会压价的
They're gonna cut our price if there's bullet holes in the walls.
- 对 钱  - 钱？  - 钞票 没错
- The money?   - Yeah, the money, the moola.
它在那儿
There he goes.
啊！开枪！
Shoot! Shoot!
- 吔…  - 你打中了钢琴！你打中了钢琴！
- Yes...   - You hit the piano! You hit the piano!
嘘…
Shh...
你疯了吗？你在房子里乱开枪！
What are you, crazy? You're blowin' the whole house up!
毁了一切都没有打到老鼠！
The only thing you haven't hit is the mouse!
你干嘛不把枪给我试一试？
Why don't you give somebody else a chance with that gun?
你干得非常好
You're doing a wonderful job.
噢！你打中它了！
Whoa! You got him!
快快快 快！
G-G-Get him!
下地狱吧！老鼠
See you in hell, mouse!
开枪！
Fire!
我讨厌那只老鼠！
God, I hate that mouse!
听到提示音后 请留言
When you hear the beep, start talking.
斯曼兹先生 我是泽普科财团的威尼
Mr. Smuntz, this is Vinny from Zeppco calling.
我们在广场等了一个小时 你却没来
We waited in the square for over an hour, but you never showed.
这种态度 我们很不满意
We do not appreciate being treated this way,
尤其在你弟弟拒绝了我们慷慨报价之后
especially after your brother already turned down our generous offer.
这次交易 就此作罢
Consider our proposal withdraw.
拉尔斯
Lars,
- 被亲哥哥背叛！  - 背叛？
- Betrayed by my own brother!   - Betrayal?
少跟我说什么背叛 你应该告诉我报价的事！
Don't talk to me about betrayal. You should have told me about that offer!
- 厂子有一半是我的  - 还有一半…
- Half that factory is mine.   - And half is mi...
那另一半是我的 你没有权利卖掉
And half is mine, including the half that you tried to sell.
如果不是被公交车撞了 我早卖了！
Yes, and would have, if it hadn't been for that stinkin' bus!
公交？你一个人呆着就惹事 对吗？你毁了这一切！
Bus? You can't leave well enough alone, can you? You ruin everything!
我？这事你怪我？
Me? You... You blame me for this?
看呐！你把地板打了个洞！
Well, look! You blew a hole in the floor!
对 但我清楚地记得有人大喊“开枪！开枪！”
Yeah, well, I distinctly remember somebody yelling, "Shoot! Shoot!"
对 可是你以前从不听我的话！
Y-Yeah, well, you've never listened to me before!
- 知道为什么吗？  - 为什么？
- And you know why?   - Why?
因为我根本看不起你！
Because I have no respect for you!
你一辈子耗在那家破烂工厂里！
Spending your whole life in that stupid factory!
真可悲
It's tragic.
你以为我没有其他的人生目标吗？
You think I didn't have other things I wanted to do with my life?
你以为我没有自己的抱负吗？
You think I didn't have ambitions of my own?
- 噢 得了 你喜欢绳子  - 我不喜欢绳子！
- Come on. You loved string.   - I didn't love string!
行了 别骗我了！
Come on, don't lie to me!
你和爸爸总是挤在一起
You and Pop were always huddled together
摆弄破绳子
running some piece of something through your fingers.
我干什么都不重要 好像我根本不存在一样！
It didn't matter what I did. I didn't even exist!
他七十大寿那天 我特意为他做了小羊排…
I made him my special rack of lamb for his 70th birthday...
- 噢 不！  - 是的！你记得
- Oh, no!   - Yes! You remember.
我费劲了心思 确保一切都做得很完美
I slaved over that meal, making sure everything was perfect.
他说过:“谢谢 厄尼 真好吃”吗？
Did he say, "Thanks, Ernie, it was delicious"?
没有
No.
他只注意到我绑肉的绳子
He only noticed the string I had tied it with.
他是疯子！
He was crazy!
可我想得到他的认可
But I still wanted his approval.
不是我要走 我是被赶走的
I didn't leave, Lars. I was cast out.
你又来了！
There you go again!
把一切都怪到别人的头上
Blaming everything else but yourself.
你以为你很成功吗？
You think you're a success!
嗯？
Huh?
你… 不懂… 烹饪！
Well, you... can't... cook!
我恨你！
I hate you!
我也恨你！
And I hate you!
- 比不上我恨你！  - 是吗？
- Not as much as I hate you!   - Yeah?
对 翻倍 翻倍！
Yeah. Double. Double!
- 哈哈哈  - 给我一样东西 我要砸你的脑袋！
Oh, give me something! I'm gonna brain you!
这个怎么样？
Here it is!
有本事扔啊 来啊！
Oh, yeah, give it to me, then! Go ahead!
你杀了它！
You killed him!
哇嗷！
Wow!
我 我不知道它在那儿！
I-I didn't even know he was there!
早知道这样 一开始就该向它扔水果…
Just think of all the trouble we could have saved ourselves...
能省多少麻烦呐！
if we just threw fruit at him in the first place!
噢 看呐！它还在喘气！
Oh, look! H-He's still breathing!
哎 杀了它！杀了它！去找硬东西 快！
Well, kill him! Kill him! Find a blunt object!
我去找 那儿有…
There you go. Get the...
- 来吧 等着瞧…  - 给它一下子
- Come on, wait and see...   - Let him have it.
- 我 我…  - 你还在等什么？
- I-I...   - What the hell are you waiting for?
- 我不能用铲子拍它  - 为什么？
- I can't just hit him with a shovel.   - Why not?
你看 它多可怜啊
Well, look at him. He's pathetic.
可怜？它是长着尾巴的希特勒
Pathetic? He's Hitler with a tail.
是长胡子的恶灵 连大预言家都没料到它的出现
This is The Omen with whiskers. Nostradamus didn't see this thing coming.
- 厄尼 它… 它是一条生命啊  - 活不长了 给我！
- We... Well, Ernie, he's a living thing.   - Not for long. Gimme that!
我做不到！
I can't!
天呐！
God!
你看它那么躺着
Look at him just lying there.
这样做不符合体育精神
It just doesn't feel very sportsmanlike.
要行动就得快！它要醒了
We better do something quick! I think he's coming to.
哦 我忘了给盒子钻孔了
Ah, I forgot to put holes in the box.
美国邮局
祝你一路顺风 小臭耗子！
Hasta la vista, you little rat bastard!
快点儿 还有正事要干呐
Come on. We got work to do.
- 两天以后 我们就发财了  - 没错
- Two days till payday, my friend.   - Yeah.
该死的美国佬
总是想占我们的便宜
■
邮资不足
古巴 哈瓦那市
菲德尔·卡斯特罗 收
退回寄件人
□
太棒了 十年来建筑史最大的发现
Perfect. It's the architectural find of the decade.
噢 我们走…
Oh, let's go...
- 来吧？  - 好的
- Shall we?   - Yes.
- 说实话 很不容易 但我们终于做到了  - 嗯哼
- Well, it wasn't easy, but we finally made it.   - Mm-hmm.
厄尼 我要送你一件东西
Ernie, I want you to have something.
是老爸的幸运绳
Pop's lucky piece of string.
- 很高兴你没扔  - 他希望我们分享
- I'm glad you kept it.   - He, uh, he wanted us to share it.
我有一种感觉…
I don't know why, but...
如果老爸在这里…
I think if he were here right now,
他会为你感到骄傲的
he'd be proud of you.
他会为我们骄傲
I think he'd be proud of us.
你们好 小姐们 多么迷人呐！欢迎！
Hello, ladies. How magnificent! Welcome!
拉尔斯 记得英格丽和希尔德吗？
Lars, you remember Ingrid and Hilde.
您好
Hello.
噢 小姐们
Ah, ladies,
你们的发型就像得到了圣经的保佑！
your hair looks positively biblical!
噢 谢谢
Oh, thank you.
噢 失陪一下 我得去看看法式薄饼
Well, if you will excuse me, I have to check on my crepes.
继续上香槟 他们喝得越多 出价越高
Keep the champagne coming, boys. The more they drink, the higher they bid.
嗨 好一场盛大的聚会呀
Hey, you boys put on quite a shindig here, huh?
承蒙夸奖 法尔科先生
Thank you so much, Mr. Falko.
你看 这么盛大的拍卖会…
You know, it would be very, very sad...
如果没人出价 那该多惨呐
if you boys put on this auction and nobody bid.
我们一定会非常难过
That would put a real crimp in our evening,
不过… 我认为不会发生那种事
but...I don't think there's any danger of that happening.
不好说 有一帮欧洲败类 围着虾狼吞虎咽呐
I don't know. There's a lot of Eurotrash out there scarfin' up the shrimps.
这样吧
I tell you what.
你取消拍卖… 就现在…
You call off the auction... now...
我给你开张支票…
and I will write you a check...
一千万
for ten millions.
这种丧失理智的慷慨 我必须拒绝
As insanely generous as that is, I have to decline,
不过我很感激你的细心体贴
but I do appreciate your thoughtful concern.
祝你玩儿得开心
Enjoy the party.
难道你喜欢线轴？
Are you interested in spooling?
呃 那当然 我父亲…
Oh, sure. My father...
呃 我是说 我和我哥哥拥有一家制绳厂
I mean, my brother and l own a string factory.
哦 真的？
Really?
嗯
Um.
有机会能去你的工厂看看吗？
I would love to see your factory sometime.
真的吗？
Really?
噢 你好 艾普尔 太意外了
Oh, hello, April. What a surprise.
你突发奇想 想过来看看？
Just dropping by for no reason, I suppose?
妻子不需要理由 哦 你在办聚会？
Does a wife need a reason? Oh, are you entertaining?
- 你是说“前妻”吧？  - 还不是
- Don't you mean "ex-wife"?   - Not quite yet.
- 啊 伟大的酋长  - 这薄饼… 太没味了
- Ah, hakuna matata.   - This crepe... c'est magnifique.
- 葡萄干 口感太棒了  - 的确很好吃
- The raisins are a nice touch.   - They are good, aren't they?
葡萄干？
Raisins?
■
邮资不足
古巴 哈瓦那市
菲德尔·卡斯特罗 收
退回寄件人
□
女士们先生们 请大家就座
Ladies and gentlemen, please take your seats.
本次拍卖即将开始
We are about to start the auction.
真不知道该祝贺你 还是为你祈祷
Lars, I don't know whether to congratulate you or wish you luck.
- 祝我们好运吧！  - 你好 艾普尔
- Wish us luck!   - Hello, April.
- 哦 你好  - 很高兴又见面了
- Oh, hello.   - Nice to see you again.
- 你认识我们的律师？  - 我随便客套两句
- I didn't know you knew our lawyer.   - It's just an expression.
女士们先生们 感谢大家参与这个重大的时刻
Thank you, ladies and gentlemen, for joining us for this momentous occasion,
本次拍卖的标的物是…
the auction of our one item up for bid,
拉鲁的遗作
the missing LaRue.
在拍卖开始之前 我想向大家介绍…
Before we start, I would like to introduce you...
这一建筑奇迹的拥有者
to the very fortunate owner of this architectural wonder,
厄尼·斯曼兹先生
Mr. Ernest Smuntz.
感谢大家的光临
Thank you, all, for coming.
先父将这栋了不起的房子留给了我弟弟拉尔斯…
When my father left this extraordinary house to my brother Lars...
和我时 我们…
and myself, uh, we...
并不知道等待我们的是何种奇迹 或者是…
had no idea what surprises were in store for us or...
何种命运
what was going to happen next.
呃
Uh,
历史协会的索普先生
when Quincy Thorpe of the, uh...
告诉我们房子的价值后
Historical Society told us of its value,
我们…
you, uh...
you could have knocked...
大吃一惊
us over with a feather.
像被…
We...
幸运星… 砸中了！
didn't know what...hit us!
翻新工程耗时耗力 但是非常值得
The renovation was exhausting but ultimately rewarding.
这座年久失修的老房子
The house was in terrible disrepair,
只需要钉几个钉子…
but nothing that a few nails...
我想 再干点儿力气活儿就修好了
and some old-fashioned elbow grease couldn't fix.
- 我相信大家等不及 想出价了  - 什么？
- I'm sure the people are eager to get to the bidding.   - What?
出价？
The bidding?
- 出价！  - 好的 谢谢
- The bidding!   - All right. Thank you.
谢谢你 斯曼兹先生
Thank you, Mr. Smuntz.
无论发生什么事都别停
No matter what happens, keep going.
建于1876年 拉鲁已知的最后一件作品
Built in 1876, the last LaRue known in existence
拥有五间卧室…
has five bedrooms...
- 看见了吗？  - 是的！  - 我就知道
- Did you see him?   - Yes!   - I thought so.
- 它吃了绳子  - 什么？
- He ate the string.   - What?
绳子 老爸的幸运绳！
The string. Pop's lucky string!
它把绳子给吃了！
The son of a bitch ate it!
你是不是早就看见了？
Why didn't you tell me you saw him?
我没看见 我只找到了这个
I didn't, but I found this.
- 你该按重量贴邮票  - 抱歉
- I told you you should have weighed him.   - I'm sorry.
- 它往哪儿跑了？  - 不知道 但跑不远
- Did you see where it went?   - No, but it can't have gone far.
那么 底价是一百万美元？
Well, shall we start the bidding at $1 million?
我们都知道 这是拉鲁的遗作
Now, we all know we're here to bid on the missing LaRue.
那么有人愿意出五十万美元吗？
Shall we start the bidding at $500,000?
很好 日本先生愿意出价五十万
Very good. I have $500,000 from the gentleman from Japan.
- 有人出一百万吗？一百万美元？  - 一百万
- Now can I hear a million? Can I hear one million?   - A million.
我出一百五十万
I'll give you one and a half.
一百五十万美元 有人出两百万吗？
I have $1.5 million. Will someone give me two?
噢…
Oh...
它在那儿！
There he is!
女士们先生们 请允许我提醒各位…
Ladies and gentleman, I'd like to remind you...
这里所有的地毯和挂毯
that all the carpets and tapestries
均为土耳其高档手织工艺品…
were woven by hand in the Honess Valley in Northern Turkey.
你好
Hello.
现在 有高于一百五十万的吗？
Now, can I have an advance on 1.5? May I have two?
两百万 谁愿意出价两百万？
Can I have two, ladies and gentlemen?
两百万！
Two million!
有人出两百万了
I have $2 million.
两百万 女士们先生们 还有更高的吗？
I have $2 million, ladies and gentlemen. Can I have an advance?
- 高于两百万的出价？  - 噢 你真漂亮
- Can I have an advance on $2 million?   - Oh, you look so beautiful.
女士们先生们 我想请大家注意看这些…
Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to draw your attention to the Lincrusia details...
铜器 镶金边 以及锡铅合金的叶子…
of the gold and silver-leafed copper and pewter...
女士们先生们 有人出价吗？
Ladies and gentlemen, can I have an advance?
高于两百万的出价？
An advance on $2 million?
有人出三百万吗？
May I hear $3 million?
纽约来的女士愿意出价三百万
I have $3 million from the lady from New York City.
- 哼！  - 你在干什么？
- Hum!   - What are you doing?
- 呃 呃 呃…  - 四百万呢？
- Uh, uh, uh...   - Four million?
有人出更高价吗？
Can I have an advance?
没什么！
Nothing!
- 把你的手拿出来！  - 谁愿意出四百万？
- Get your hand out of there immediately!   - May I hear $4 million?
太过份了！
Too much!
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
- 或许大家已经注意到了…  - 马上就好 马上就好了！
Wait! Wait just a minute!
拿出来！
Take it out!
…这两块镶花地板…
...These two parquet floor boards...
- 马上就好！马上就好！  - …是摩洛哥所设计
- Wait! Wait just a minute!   - ...are designed by Morocco.
现在有人出价四百万吗？
Now may I hear four million dollars?
太棒了！
That's great!
四百万！
Four million!
呃 日本先生出价四百万美元
$4 million from the gentleman from Japan.
摸到了！
I got it!
呃
Uh,
酋长出五百万
the sheikh bids $5 million.
- 谢谢酋长  - 我抓到了
- Thank you, sir.   - I've got you now.
五百万美元
$5 million.
有人愿意出更高的价格吗？
Can I have an advance on...on $5 million?
女士们先生们 五百万美元
Ladies and gentlemen, $5 million.
还有更高价吗？
Can I have an advance?
这可是拉鲁的遗作
It's the missing LaRue.
现在出价五百万
The bidding stands at $5 million,
- 女士们先生们…  - 小子！  - 哎 别松手
- ladies and gentlemen...   - my little friend!   - Hold on tight.
我把它弄出来！
I'm gonna get it out!
噢 天呐
Oh, god.
哎 好了
Hey. Okay.
拉鲁遗作五百万美元
Uh, $5 million for the missing LaRue.
- 它就在我的手里  - 是吗？好了
- It's in my hand.   - Is it? Okay.
你还没碰到它吗？
Haven't you touched it yet?
- 女士们先生们 有人愿意出六百万吗？  - 它跑了！
- Ladies and gentlemen, can I have an advance on five? Will someone give me $6 million?   - It's gone!
- 六百万  - 谢谢 先生
- Six million.   - Thank you, sir.
- 希尔德 你的线轴冒烟了！  - 有人出价六百万美元
- Hilde, the spool is smoking!   - I have $6 million.
还有人出更高价吗？
May I have an advance?
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen.
高于六百万？
An advance on $6 million?
现在的出价是六百万美元
The bidding stands at six million dollars.
- 噢 快想办法！  - 七百万
- Oh, do something!   - Seven million.
- 快想办法！  - 七百万美元 谢谢你 先生
- Find a way!   - Seven million dollars. Thank you, sir.
七百万美元 还有更高价吗？
I have seven. Any advance on seven?
七百万
Seven million.
女士们先生们 七百万美元
Ladies and gentlemen. Seven million dollars.
有人出八百万元吗？
May I hear Eight million dollars?
- 天呐！  - 让她离墙远一点儿！
- God!   - Keep her away from the walls!
这房子是无价之宝！
The house is priceless!
您继续！
Keep goin'!
哦 好 好 好
Oh, yes, yes, yes.
七百五十万？
C-C-Can I have 7.5?
法尔科先生！
Mr. Falko!
- 现在我们…  - 法尔科先生！
- I have...   - Mr. Falko!
…哦 有人出八百万
...Oh, $8 million over there.
八百万美元一次
$8 million going once,
八百万两次…
$8 million going twice...
八百万？八百万？你应该接受那张支票！
$8 million? $8 million? You should have taken the check!
- 真是大白痴！  - 你给我闭嘴！你这个…
- What an idiot!   - You shut up! You...
一千万！
Ten millions!
哦 一千万 一千一百万呢？
Oh, ten million dollars. Can I have 11?
日本先生出价一千一百万
I have $11 million from the gentleman from Japan.
一千二百五十万
Twelve.
一千三百万
Thirteen.
一千四百
Fourteen.
一千五百
Fifteen.
- 厄尼·斯曼兹先生出价一千六百万  - 错了！
- $16 million from Ernie Smuntz.   - No!
大白痴！
Big idiot!
- 一千七百万  - 一千七百万 谢谢 先生 一千七百万
- 17 million.   - $17 million. Thank you, sir. I have $17 million.
有人愿意出更高的价钱吗？
Any advance on seventeen?
灭火呀！
Fire fighting!
- 好险呐！  - 好主意
- How dangerous!   - Good idea.
等我口令 把水龙头开到最大 把它冲出来
When I tell you to, turn it on full blast. We'll flush him out.
开！
Now!
- 一千八百万  - 纽约小姐出价一千八百万
- $18 million.   - $18 million from the lady from New York City.
- 谢谢 一千八百万  - 你根本没那么多钱
- Thank you. $18 million.   - You don't have that kind of money.
- 厄尼  - 等会  - 有人出价一千九百万吗？
- Ernie?   - Not now.   - May I hear $19 million?
一千九百万？
$19 million?
- 两千万  - 两千万 谢谢 法尔科先生！
- Twenty millions.   - Twenty million. Thank you. Mr. Falko.
有人出两千一百万吗？
Can I hear twenty-one?
日本先生出价两千一百万
$21 million from the gentleman from Japan.
还有人出更高价吗？
May I have an advance?
- 两千一百万？  - 两千二百万 不能再高了
- Any advance?   - Twenty-two million. That's my last offer.
两千二百万一次…
Twenty-two million going once...
两千五百万
25 millions.
25 million dollars.
谢谢 先生
Thank you, sir.
两千五百万
25 million dollars.
当前出价是两千五百万美元 还有更高价吗？
The bidding stands at $25 million. Do I have an advance?
两千五百万美元一次
$25 million going once,
两千五百万美元两次…
$25 million going twice...
哎 等等 你们去哪儿？
Hey, wait. Where are you going?
我还能找到 真的 等等 女士
I can still find it. Really. Wait, ma'am.
就一小会儿 我能再找个拉鲁的房子
Just a little while. I can find another LaRu's house.
嘿！别走！
Hey! Don't go!
这些水只是 只是…
The water was just a...
为了演示… 拉鲁的房子
a demonstration of... of how durable...
有多么坚固
a LaRue really is.
怎么样？
How about that?
知道了吧？这房子永远不会塌
Now you know this house will last forever.
爸爸的幸运绳
Pop's lucky string.
我们干掉它了
I guess we got him.
是 应该是
Yeah, I guess we did.
什么声音？
What was that?
拉尔斯！你看！
Lars! Look!
是绳子
It's string.
奶酪的
It's cheese.
工厂经过整体改造之后…
The entire factory has been retrofitted...
积极投入奶酪制品的加工生产
to facilitate the manufacturing of cheese-based products.
是这样
I see.
那是新型无乳糖奶糖生产线
And over here we're developing our new lactose-free line.
- 那边呢？  - 哦 那是质检处
- What is that?   - Oh, that's quality control.
尽情吃吧
Here you go. Knock yourself out.
哦 不好吃？奥蒂斯 多放咖喱
Oh. No good, huh? Otis, more curry.
好 尝尝这个
Okay. Try this one.
嗯？马苏里拉奶酪加青鱼
Huh? It's mozzarella and herring.
有鱼味儿吧？
You can taste the herring, right?
我还要为孩子生产鱼子酱加布里干酪…
I've also got a great idea for a caviar-brie swirl,
和花生酱 加波萝伏洛干酪
and a peanut butter and jelly provolone for the kids.
不过我真正想和你商量的是开拓市场
But what I really want to talk to you about is expansion and marketing.
让你来做我们的代言人
I think you should be our spokesperson.
以前有人用老鼠做过代言 效果相当不错
I know some people who've used a mouse as a spokesperson, and it seemed to work out well.
我想把这里变成最先进的绳子奶酪工厂
You see, I want to turn this into the string cheese factory of tomorrow today...
让它成为经久不衰的佳肴…
Make it an enduring delicacy...
--鲁道夫·斯曼兹
“没有绳子的世界是混乱的”